A Finding Aid to the Leonard Bocour Papers and Business Records, 1933-1993, in the Archives of American Art AAA.bocoleon
Archives of American Art
Leonard Bocour papers and business records
1933-1993
AAA.bocoleon
Archives of American Art
11.8 Linear feet
The papers of American art collector, paint manufacturer, lecturer, and painter, Leonard Bocour measure 11.8 linear feet and date from 1933 to 1993. Found within the papers are biographical material; miscellaneous correspondence with artists and colleagues, including Helen Frankenthaler, Chaim Gross, Philip Guston, Alex Katz, Jack Levine, Morris Louis, David Oxtoby, and Philip Pearlstein; diaries, daily calendars, notes and writings; personal business records and the business records of Bocour Artist Colors, Inc.; transcripts of interviews with Bocour; and printed material.
Bocour, Leonard, 1910-1993
Biographical Note
American art collector, paint manufacturer, lecturer, and painter, Leonard Bocour (nèe Leonard Bogdanoff) was born in 1910 in New York City. He studied at the National Academy of Design and at the Art Students League. In 1928, he met German artist Emil Ganso who taught him how to make artists' colors.
In 1932, Bocour established Bocour Hand Ground Artist Colors and sold paint directly to artists, greatly increasing his contacts and acquaintances in the art community. In this Depression era, Bocour often gave away paint to struggling artists who later became successful. Because artists would sometimes trade art work for tubes of paint, Bocour was able to build an impressive art collection that he would later loan for exhibition. He also donated numerous works of art to schools and museums.
Over the years, Bocour maintained a close relationship with artists, most notably Helen Frankenthaler, Philip Guston, Jack Levine, Morris Louis, and Philip Pearlstein. In the late 1930s, Bocour decided to increase his business by selling through retailers and wholesalers, gradually building a successful business.
From 1945 to 1955, Bocour joined the Skowhegan School of Painting and Sculpture in Maine and for many years taught a summer technical course. In 1947, he developed Magna, an acrylic resin miscible with oil or turpentine that had the same consistency as oil paint, but dried in a fraction of the time. In 1960, Bocour introduced Aqua-Tec which is an acrylic polymer emulsion miscible with water.
From 1952 to 1970, Samuel Golden was Bocour's partner in the capacity of production manager. A merger with Zipatone, Inc. was carried out in 1982, but was dissolved in 1987. Zipatone, Inc. moved the company to Chicago, but Bocour remained in New York as president and consultant.
Beginning in the early 1960s, Bocour lectured at art schools and various arts organizations, discussing drawing, painting, and different art media as well as demonstrating his own products. He was a member of the National Art Materials Trade Association (NAMTA) and was president of the Art Material Manufacturers' Association, inducted into its Hall of Fame in 1974. Leonard Bocour died on Labor Day 1993.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of American art collector, paint manufacturer, lecturer, and painter, Leonard Bocour measure 11.8 linear feet and date from 1933 to 1993. Found within the papers is biographical material, including identity cards, membership cards, and award certificates. Miscellaneous correspondence is primarily with artists and colleagues, including Helen Frankenthaler, Chaim Gross, Philip Guston, Alex Katz, Jack Levine, Morris Louis, David Oxtoby, and Philip Pearlstein and discuss exhibitions and other art-related topics. Also found are diaries and annotated daily calendars; personal business records regarding personal finances, donations, and lectures; business records for Bocour Artist Colors, Inc., including contracts, business correspondence, financial documentation, and printed material; notes and writings including address books and writings by Bocour and others; transcripts of interviews with Bocour that discuss his early career; and printed material including clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs, booklets, and brochures.
Arrangement
The collection has been arranged into eight series primarily according to type of material. Materials within each series have been arranged chronologically, except for the Receipts for "Private Deals" and the Business Card File which are arranged alphabetically. Oversized material from various series has been housed in Box 13 and OV 14 and is noted in the Series Description/Container Listings Section at the appropriate folder title.
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1940s-1990s (Box 1; 4 folders)
Series 2: Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1950s-1990s (Box 1-4, 13, OV 14; 3.8 linear feet)
Series 3: Diaries and Annotated Calendars, 1955-1987 (Box 4-5; 19 folders)
Series 4: Personal Business Records, circa 1961-1992 (Box 5-7, 13; 2.2 linear feet)
Series 5: Business Records for Bocour Artist Colors, Inc., circa 1942-1992 (Box 7-9, 13; 2.3 linear feet)
Series 6: Notes and Writings, 1960-1993, undated (Box 9-10; 0.8 linear feet)
Series 7: Interview Transcripts, 1970s-1980s (Box 10; 5 folders)
Series 8: Printed Material, 1933-1993, undated (Box 10-13; 1.8 linear feet)
Related Material
Additional Leonard Bocour papers may be found at the Syracuse University Library, Special Collections Research Center.
Provenance
The Leonard Bocour papers and business records were donated by his widow, Ruth Bocour, in 1994.
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open for research. Use requires an appointment.
Bocour Artist Colors (Firm).; Collectors and collecting--New York (State)--New York; Diaries; Drawing--Technique; Interviews; Paint industry and trade--New York (State)--New York; Painting--Equipment and supplies; Painting--Technique
- Biographical Material, 1940s-1990s; Series 1; 4 Folders Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  Biographical material consists of biographical notes, identity and membership cards, award certificates for Bocour, and a photocopy of his son's birth certificate.
  - Biographical Notes and Birth Certificate for Peter Bocour, 1947-1990 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Identity Cards and Blood Donation Card, 1944-1984 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Membership Cards, 1950-1990 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Award Certificates, 1950-1980 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1950s-1990s; Series 2; 3.8 Linear feet Box 1 -4, 13, OV 14
  Correspondence consists primarily of letters exchanged with business colleagues and artists including Helen Frankenthaler, John Grillo, Chaim Gross, Philip Guston, Grace Hartigan, Alex Katz, Jack Levine, Morris Louis, Eugene Massin, Nathan Oliveira, David Oxtoby, and Philip Pearlstein, discussing exhibitions and other art-related topics. There are single letters from Anthony Caro, actor Robert DeNiro, Jimmy Ernst, Philip Evergood, Emil Ganso, Leon Golub, Frederick Hartt, Helen Hayes, Al Held, Joseph Hirshhorn, Ibram Lassaw, Jacob Lawrence, Roy Lichtenstein, Bill Mauldin, Alice Neel, Kenneth Noland, Jules Olitski, Gabor Peterdi, Ad Reinhart, George Rickey, James Rosenquist, Moses Soyer, Raphael Soyer, Frank Stella, and Jack Tworkov.
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1954-1972, undated (Box 1, Folder 5-74)
    Oversized material housed in Box 13, Folder 1, and OV 14.
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1973-1977 (Box 2, Folder 1-71)
    Oversized material housed in Box 13, Folder 1.
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1978-1984 (Box 3, Folder 1-66)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1985-1993 (Box 4, Folder 1-59)
  - Oversized Illustrated Letter from Jeffrey Dunn, undated (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Oversized Letter from Ann Marie Rousseau, undated (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Oversized Exhibition Poster Enclosed in Letter from James Suzuki, 1973 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Oversized Letter from David Oxtoby, 1973 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Oversized Letter from David Sutherland, 1986 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Oversized Letter from Jonah Kinigstein, 1991 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Two Oversized Letters from David Oxtoby, 1968, 1969 (Box OV 14)
  - Oversized Exhibition Poster Enclosed in Letter from T. Kawashima, 1972 (Box OV 14)
- Diaries and Annotated Calendars, 1955-1987; Series 3; 19 Folders Box 4, 5
  Thirty-two diaries and nine annotated calendars contain brief notes about daily activities.
  - Diaries, 1955-1963 (Box 4, Folder 60-63)
  - Diaries, 1964-1987 (Box 5, Folder 1-12)
  - Annotated Calendars, 1970-1986 (Box 5, Folder 13-15)
- Personal Business Records, 1961-1992; Series 4; 2.2 Linear feet Box 5-7, 13
  Personal Business Records include documents concerning Bocour's art collection and his public outreach activities. These records reflect business transactions not directly related to the operations of Bocour Artist Colors, Inc. Bocour's donations were primarily of art work to schools and museums. His lectures focused on drawing and painting and demonstrated his paint products.
  - Personal Income Tax Returns, 1974-1979 (Box 5, Folder 16-17)
  - List of Art Work in Bocour Collection, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Appraisal Reports on Art Work Owned by Bocour, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Miscellaneous Receipts, 1961-1992 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence Regarding Donations of Art Work, 1961-1968 (Box 5, Folder 21-31)
  - Correspondence Regarding Donations of Art Work, 1969-1992 (Box 6, Folder 1-34)
  - Correspondence Regarding Lectures and Demonstrations, 1961-1977, undated (Box 6, Folder 35-61)
    Oversized material housed in Box 13, Folder 2.
  - Correspondence Regarding Lectures and Demonstrations, 1978-1987 (Box 7, Folder 1-65)
  - Oversized Poster and List of Lectures by Bocour for Tempo Gallery, undated (Box 13, Folder 2)
- Business Records for Bocour Artist Colors, Inc., circa 1942-1992; Series 5; 2.3 Linear feet Box 7-9, 13
  These records document business transactions conducted by Bocour Artist Colors, Inc. and include financial records, correspondence with other companies, and business- related printed material. Files marked as "Private Deals" reflect Bocour's practice of trading tubes of paint and other art products in exchange for original art work.
  - Trademark Application, 1942-1943 (Box 7, Folder 66)
  - Court Documents Concerning Name Change to Bocour, 1949-1951 (Box 7, Folder 67)
  - Leases, 1958-1983 (Box 7, Folder 68)
  - Contracts with Samuel Golden, 1954-1968 (Box 7, Folder 69-72)
  - Structural File Concerning Purchase of Shares of Samuel Golden, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 73)
  - Contract with Oskar Vangerow, 1975 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Contract with Rick Farrell, 1977 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Contract with Plaid Enterprises, Inc., 1977 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Contract with Union Local 810, 1981-1983 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Contract with Zipatone, Inc., 1982 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Tax Records, 1977-1987 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Records Concerning Stocks, 1982-1985 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence with Inter-Society Color Council, 1971-1982, undated (Box 8, Folder 8-13)
  - Correspondence with Heinz Jordan & Co., Ltd., 1972-1986 (Box 8, Folder 14-22)
  - Correspondence with Zipatone, Inc., 1979-1991 (Box 8, Folder 23-39)
  - Correspondence with Oskar Vangerow KG, 1976-1992 (Box 8, Folder 40-51)
  - Address List of Customers, undated (Box 8, Folder 52)
  - Notes from Meetings, 1982-1983 (Box 8, Folder 53-54)
  - Miscellaneous Notes, undated (Box 8, Folder 55)
  - Ledger of Comparative Balance Sheets, 1946-1948 (Box 8, Folder 56)
  - Ledger of "L. B. Deals", 1963-1978 (Box 8, Folder 57)
  - Ledger of Annual Sales Totals, 1967-1982 (Box 8, Folder 58-59)
    Oversized material housed in Box 13, Folder 4.
  - Receipts for "Private Deals," Paintings Received, 1963-1971 (Box 8, Folder 60-71)
  - Receipts for "Private Deals," Paintings Not Received, 1959-1971 (Box 8, Folder 72-80)
  - Receipts for "Private Deals," Paintings Not Received, 1959-1971 (Box 9, Folder 1-10)
  - Receipts for Miscellaneous Deals, 1971-1978 (Box 9, Folder 11-13)
  - Invoices from Tiffany & Co., 1985-1987 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Comparative Sales Report, 1963-1965 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Product Inventories, 1981 (Box 9, Folder 16-18)
  - Notes about Products, undated (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Reports: Product Sales & Costs and Salesmen's Performance, 1983-1984 (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - Reports: Sales Representative's Commission, 1984-1988 (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - Auditor's Reports, 1955-1983 (Box 9, Folder 22-41)
  - Label Designs, 1961-1972, undated (Box 9, Folder 42-44)
    Oversized material housed in Box 13, Folder 11.
  - Miscellaneous Booklets, 1963-1965 (Box 9, Folder 45)
  - Brochures for Aqua-Tec Paint, undated (Box 9, Folder 46)
  - Brochures for Bellini Paint, undated (Box 9, Folder 47)
  - Brochures for Casein Paint, undated (Box 9, Folder 48)
  - Brochures for Magna Paint, undated (Box 9, Folder 49)
  - Brochures for Miscellaneous Products, undated (Box 9, Folder 50)
    Oversized material housed in Box 13, Folder 12.
  - Price Lists and Order Forms, 1964-1979 (Box 9, Folder 51)
  - Art Material Directory, 1980 (Box 9, Folder 52)
  - Directory of Suppliers, 1982 (Box 9, Folder 53)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, undated (Box 9, Folder 54)
  - Oversized Address List of Customers, undated (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Oversized Ledger of Annual Sales Totals, 1967-1973 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Oversized Reports of Product Sales and Costs, 1983-1984 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Oversized Reports of Salesmen's Performances, 1984 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Oversized Sales Representative's Commission Report, 1984-1988 (Box 13, Folder 7-10)
  - Oversized Label Designs, 1972 (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Oversized Brochure for Zipatone Products, undated (Box 13, Folder 12)
- Notes and Writings, 1960-1993, undated; Series 6; 0.8 Linear feet Box 9-10
  Notes consist primarily of address books and a file of colleagues' business cards. Writings by Bocour include autobiographical accounts, miscellaneous poems and typescripts about Emil Ganso, Eugene Massin, David Oxtoby, and various art-related topics. Writings by others include a transcript of the memorial service for Gandy Brodie, a typescript about Emil Ganso, and miscellaneous artists' resumés and typescripts on various art-related topics.
  - Address Book, undated (Box 9, Folder 55-56)
  - Address Book, 1969 (Box 9, Folder 57)
  - Business Card File, undated (Box 10, Folder 1-12)
  - Miscellaneous Address Lists, undated (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous Notes, undated (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Writings by Bocour, 1966-1992, undated (Box 10, Folder 15-24)
  - Writings by Others, 1960-1993, undated (Box 10, Folder 25-34)
- Interview Transcripts, 1970s-1980s; Series 7; 5 Folders Box 10
  Four interview transcripts describe Bocour's early life and career. The interview with Abraham Joshua Heschel was conducted under the auspices of the Jewish Theological Seminary of America and in it Dr. Heschel discusses his religious beliefs and his publications.
  - Bocour Interviewed by Christopher Busa, undated (Box 10, Folder 35)
  - Interview with Bocour, 1973 (Box 10, Folder 36)
  - "A Conversation with Dr. Abraham Joshua Heschel", 1973 (Box 10, Folder 37)
  - "Lee Solomon Talking to Ruth Bocour", 1974 (Box 10, Folder 38)
  - "Conversation with Leonard Bocour", 1988 (Box 10, Folder 39)
- Printed Material, 1933-1993, undated; Series 8; 1.8 Linear feet Box 10-13
  Printed material consists primarily of clippings that reflect Bocour's enduring interest in art, artists, and art media. An exhibition catalog for Jacob Lawrence is autographed by the artist.
  - Clippings, 1949-1974, undated (Box 10, Folder 40-57)
  - Clippings, 1975-1993 (Box 11, Folder 1-29)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs for the Bocour Collection, 1962-1978, undated (Box 11, Folder 30)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs for Miscellaneous Artists, 1933-1992, undated (Box 11, Folder 31-38)
  - Press Releases, 1972-1981 (Box 11, Folder 39)
  - Programs, 1950-1976 (Box 11, Folder 40-42)
  - Booklets "Let's Draw" and "Let's Paint" by Bocour, 1977 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Booklet "Start" by Jay Folb, undated (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous School Brochures, 1947-1972, undated (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Brochures for American Federation of Arts, 1965-1973 (Box 12, Folder 4-5)
  - Century Association Yearbook, 1984 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Board of Visitors Directory, Boston University, 1977 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - NAMTA Membership Directory, 1983 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, 1962-1991, undated (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Oversized Clipping, 1967 (Box 13, Folder 13)